Jensen, Vernon H., Additional Papers /4128
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Vernon H. Jensen Additional Papers
1953-1989
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Jensen, Vernon H.
/4128
10 cubic feet
10 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
7994532
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, May 20, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 01, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Vernon Jensen (July 10, 1907 September 27, 1998) was a founding faculty member of Cornell's New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations.
A graduate of Brigham Young University (BS '32), Jensen worked as a substitute teacher in Salt Lake City after college before leaving to pursue graduate study at the University of California at Berkeley (PhD '39). Shortly before completing his degree, Jensen began teaching at the University of Colorado. He taught at UC from 1937 to 1946, during which time he also served as a consultant to the National Defense Mediation Board (1941) and a public panel member, mediator and arbitrator for the National War Labor Board (1942) and Wage Stabilization Director of the NWLB's Ninth Region (1942-1944).
Jensen was among the founding faculty of the School of Industrial and Labor Relations, joining Cornell in 1946. Jensen became Associate Dean of the ILR School in 1965 and was elected to Cornell's Board of Trustees in 1973. In addition to numerous articles, Jensen wrote four books, Lumber and Labor (1945), Heritage of Conflict (1950), Collective Bargaining in the Nonferrous Metal Industry (1955), and Hiring of Dockworkers and Employment Practices in the Ports of New York, London, Liverpool, Rotterdam, and Marseilles (1964).
See the Cornell University Faculty Memorial Statement for Professor Vernon Jensen: http://hdl.handle.net/1813/18668
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3002: Vernon H. Jensen Papers /4007: Vernon H. Jensen Additional Records /4067: Vernon H. Jensen Longshore Research Files /4096: Vernon H. Jensen Additional Research and Office Files /4128 AV: Vernon H. Jensen Audio-Visual Materials /4137: Vernon H. Jensen Additional Files 5839: Vernon Jenson Additional Arbitration Files 5902: Vernon H. Jensen Additional Arbitration Files
Jensen, Vernon H.
7994532
- Judiciary Committee (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Cornell Student Code of Conduct, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Lots of documents.
- Student Code of Conduct (Box 1, Folder 2)
  File #1
- Final Report on Student Affairs, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Student Code of Conduct (Box 1, Folder 3)
  File #2
- Student Code of Conduct (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Final Report on Student Affairs, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- How to Better Your Labor Contract, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Newspapers (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Among others, Cornell Chronicle.
- Correspondence (1 of 3 files) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence (2 of 3 files) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence (3 of 3 files) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Biographed (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Two short publications on American labor history.
- Jensen-Personal (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Medical bills, two small photo albums.
- Strife on Waterfront (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Documentation regarding the publishing.
- Retirement (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Assorted documents pertaining to the title.
- A (Box 2, Folder 5)
- B (Box 2, Folder 6)
- C (Box 2, Folder 7)
- D (Box 2, Folder 8)
- D (Box 2, Folder 8)
- E (Box 2, Folder 9)
- E (Box 2, Folder 9)
- F (Box 2, Folder 10)
- F (Box 2, Folder 10)
- G (Box 2, Folder 11)
- G (Box 2, Folder 11)
- H (Box 2, Folder 12)
- I (Box 2, Folder 13)
- J (Box 2, Folder 14)
- K (Box 2, Folder 15)
- L (Box 2, Folder 16)
- M (Box 2, Folder 17)
- N (Box 2, Folder 18)
- O (Box 2, Folder 19)
- P (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Q (Box 2, Folder 21)
- R (Box 2, Folder 22)
- S (Box 2, Folder 23)
- T (Box 2, Folder 24)
- U (Box 2, Folder 25)
- V (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Q (Box 2, Folder 27)
- W (Box 2, Folder 27)
- X,Y,Z (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Book Reviews - V.H. Jensen (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Waterfront Research Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Bethe Committee (Box 2, Folder 31)
- American Arbitration Association (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Research and Education Committee (Box 2, Folder 33)
- National Academy of Arbitrators (Box 2, Folder 34)
- McGill University Symposium, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- London Trip - Jensen (Box 2, Folder 36)
  Sept. 1967, Jan. 1969
- Collective Bargaining Conference at M.I.T., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  April 22-23
- Conference at Oregon State, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Committee Review of Judicial Proceedings for Student Misconduct, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- M.P. Catherwood (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Advisory Council on Labor Management, Improper Practices Act (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Advisory Council, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Advisory Council, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Advisory Council, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Advisory Council, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Advisory Council (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Letterhead and Vouchers
- Advisory Council (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Annual Reports, etc.
- Everett (Box 3, Folder 9)
- RADC-Georgia Tech (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Walt Ku (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Ron Larson (Box 3, Folder 12)
- RADC- General (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Seminar- TA (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Green Mountain Strike (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Mine Mill (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Mediation Study (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Drafts, Manuscripts, & Notes for George Hildebrand (Box 4, Folder 1)
- United States Postal Service Arbitration Files, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Dialogue: A journal of Mormon Thought (Box 4, Folder 3)
- 40th Anniversary Celebration of ILR, and Manuscripts (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Correspondence 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Correspondence 2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Correspondence 3 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Correspondence 4 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Correspondence 5 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Correspondence 6 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Various folders (see Notes for contents) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Among them: "Intro-Collective Bargaining," "Rise of Collective Bargaining," Administration of Labor Relations." NLRA," Process of Corporate Bargaining."
- Economics (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Manuscripts (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Works by Vernon Jensen (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Collective Bargaining (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Vancouver (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Economics (2 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Port of London Authority, Transport & General Workers Union (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Most Court (Box 6, Folder 1)
- New York State Board of Mediation and Arbitration (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Prof Sensen (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Bradley (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Department of Commerce (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, and a Paper (Box 6, Folder 6)
  Paper is on Labor Management Relations
- Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 7)
  Subfolder included.
- Copper Industry Labor Trouble (Box 6, Folder 8)
  This is a pack of folders.
- Documents to William O Dwyer (Box 6, Folder 9)
  Held in a red binder.
- Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Labor Mediation (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Proceedings of Second annual meeting of Association of State Mediation Agencies, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  June 4,5 ,1953 at New Brunswick, NJ
- Typescript for The Tragedy of Marxism (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Labor Economics (Box 6, Folder 14)
  It's a book.
- ILR300 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- ILR300 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- ILR700 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- ILR701 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- ILR500 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- CBG ILR700 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Conceptions of Collective Bargaining (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Collective Bargaining - Speeches, Articles (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Legal and Legislative (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Law - Restraint of Trade (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Labor Relations Law - National Labor Relations Act (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Labor Relations Law (Taft-Hartley Act) (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Railway Labor Act (Box 7, Folder 12)
- National War Labor Board (Box 7, Folder 13)
- NLRA - Beginnings and Early Problems (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Taft-Hartley (LMRA) (Box 7, Folder 15)
- State and Federal Jurisdiction (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Structure of Collective Bargaining (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Process and Procedures of Collective Bargaining (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Collective Bargaining - Process (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Collective Bargaining - Scope (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Settlement of Labor-Management Disputes (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Handling Industrial Controversy - General (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Settlement of Labor-Management Disputes (Mediation) (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Emergency Disputes (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Nature of Agreement (Box 7, Folder 25)
- Interpretation and Administration of Agreement (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Interpretation and Administration Agreement (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Arbitration (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Arbitration (Box 8, Folder 2)
- How Issues of S (Box 8, Folder 3)
- How Issues of Subcontracting and Plant Removal are decided by the Courts (Box 8, Folder 3)
- How Issues of subcontracting and Plant Removal are decided by the courts (Box 8, Folder 4)
- "Closed Shop" and Hiring (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Management Rights (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Seniority (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Discipline and Discharge (Box 8, Folder 7)
- The Hydra-Headed Monster: The problem of inflation in the US (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Monopoly (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Hours (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Technological Change (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Pensions (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Health and Welfare Plans (Box 8, Folder 13)
- BG - Public Sector (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Pensions - H+W (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Final Examination - ILR 700 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Labor History (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Beginnings (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Labor Movement (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Trade Union Structure (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Trade Union Government (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Trade Union Problems (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Employer Associations (Box 8, Folder 23)
- Foreign Movements (Box 8, Folder 24)
- Industries (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Organization and Government (Box 8, Folder 26)
- Left-Wing Unionism (Box 8, Folder 27)
- Union Democracy (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Theories of the Labor Movement (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Theories of Collective Bargaining (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Center for Advanced Study in Behavioral Science (Box 9, Folder 4)
- LUMBER (Box 9, Folder 5)
- The Academic Departments and the Program of the School (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Reviews and Letter, Lumber and Labor (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Dean's Annual Reports (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Fulbright Grant (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Iwa Project (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Longshore Study (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Decasualization Notes (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Hiring and Employment of Longshoremen in the Port of Greater New York (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Manuscripts (Box 9, Folder 14)
  Conflict and Strikes in Labor Relations, among others.
- International Labour Review (Box 9, Folder 15)
- History of Governmental Arbitration and mediation in the State of New York (Box 9, Folder 16)
  Bundle of several folders.
- Professor Vernon Jensen (Box 9, Folder 17)
  A bundle of folders.
- Today's Mail (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Preliminary publication of "Technology in Hiring of Dock Workers in the Port of New York" (Box 9, Folder 19)
- The Future of Collective Bargaining (Box 9, Folder 20)
- Documents/Reading List for Collective Bargaining (Box 9, Folder 21)
- Theories of Trade Unionism in the United States, by Vernon Jensen (Box 9, Folder 22)
- Bibliography of Dispute Settlement by Third Parties (Box 9, Folder 23)
  Two Copies
- Collective Bargaining, Labor Laws, Labor Movements,: Area Meetings (Box 9, Folder 24)
- Collective Bargaining, Labor Law, Labor Movements: (Box 9, Folder 25)
- Bibliography of Dispute Settlements by Third Parties (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Collective Bargaining in the Nonferrous Metals Industry by Vernon Jensen (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Hiring Arrangements and the Rule-Making Process in Certain European Ports and in Port of New York (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Collective Bargaining, article on Economic Science, two copies of Computer Hiring of Dock Workers (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Black Studies: Myths and Realities (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Publishing's by Vernon H. Jensen (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Assorted Publications and Documents related to Vernon H. Jensen (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Assorted Publications and Documents related to Ver (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Philosophical, Legal, and Practical considerations of Collective Bargaining in an Enterprise Society (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Men and Machines: A Story about Longshoring on the West Coast (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Men and Mechanics: A Story about Longshoring on the West Coast (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Book Reviews (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Bibliography of Dispute Settlement by Third Parties (Box 10, Folder 10)
- ILR300 Syllabus and Assorted Notes (Box 10, Folder 11)
- American Labor: From Conspiracy to Collective Bargaining (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Contract Negotiation: Preparation and Practice (Box 10, Folder 13)
- The V (Box 10, Folder 14)
- The Evolution of Capitalism, and an article on liberals and intellectuals (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Industrial Relations Seminar, notes by Vernon H. Jensen (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Decasualization & Modernization of Dock Work in London by Vernon H. Jensen (Box 10, Folder 16)
  Three Copies in the box
- Two Boxes of Index Cards, for Vernon H. Jensen (Box 10, Folder 17)